Steven McVey

Williamstown, Massachusetts | 971-719-3377 | steven@stevenmcvey.com LinkedIn | Blog

FULL STACK SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Teacher-Turned-Software Engineer with experience in JavaScript and Ruby-based programming. I am highly adept at integrating and applying knowledge from many different areas when problem-solving. I am adaptable, perceptive, and patient, and can sometimes be unconventional in my thinking and in the way that I approach things.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

JavaScript, React, Ruby, Rails, Active Record, Postgres, RESTful API, JSON, HTML, CSS, Git, Chinese, Korean

TECHNICAL PROJECTS

Chinese Character Test - Github | Demo | Website (UN: exampleteacher, PW: password123)

A web-based application designed for Chinese language teaching and research, enabling the assessment of students' character recognition abilities and providing comprehensive tools for viewing and analyzing test results

- Created custom database schema and REST API with Rails, Active Record, and PostgreSQL
- Integrated custom validations and error-handling
- Implemented secure passwords with BCrypt and session-based authentication to support secure login
- Designed a clean user interface with React and Bootstrap

Scamps - Github | Demo

An app for parents to sign their children up for Summer camps

- Created a full-stack web application using a Rails API backend and a React frontend, combining server-side and client-side technologies for a seamless user experience
- Implemented full CRUD actions for resources, following RESTful routing conventions for backend routes
- Incorporated user authentication and authorization features according to the latest industry standards

EXPERIENCE

Salem Keizer Public Schools, Salem, Oregon

10/2021 - 06/2022

Science Teacher

- Designed and implemented engaging lessons to expose students to the importance of science in understanding the world around them
- Actively sought out professional development opportunities to further enhance behavior management techniques and teaching methodologies, staying up-to-date with best practices in science education

Jianzhong Kindergarten, Zhuhai, China

Bachelor of Arts in Chinese Language and Literature

10/2015 - 01/2020

Pre-school Teacher

- Created and delivered English immersion lessons catering to the unique needs and learning styles of young students
- Collaborated with fellow teachers to share best practices, develop innovative teaching strategies, and participate in professional development activities
- Achieved outstanding results in student English proficiency levels, consistently receiving praise from local elementary teachers for our students' exceptional language skills

EDUCATION

Flatiron School Full Stack Web Development, Ruby on Rails, and JavaScript program	2022 - 2023
Willamette University, Salem, Oregon Master of Arts in teaching Chinese and Mathematics	2012 - 2013
National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan Year-long intensive International Chinese Language Program (ICLP)	2011 - 2012
University of Oregon, Eugene, Oregon	2007-2011